We move on and talk about variables because they are central to any programming language.
These are like containers which hold your value and the data keeps on varying, the data keeps
on changing.
That's why they are in fact called variables.
And I remember what I had listened to in my many years back in my C-tution class about
what is a variable that is name of location and memory where data can be stored.
Again, I'll repeat it for you.
Name in location, name of location and memory where data can be stored.
So you need to store data, right?
And you need a container, guess what in programming languages we have variable.
So people coming in here from other languages, they will know what variables are and they
will just see how do we do that in Java and what is the variation.
But people who are just starting to code that's important for you to understand that is
it's just the name of the container in memory for you.
And how do you use variables, how do we declare variables in Java is we just say the data
type and then the identifier.
So now this time on line number 16, the identifier is something which resembles your variable.
Here at line number 7, the identifier was the name of the class.
At line number 9, it was the name of the method, but at line number 16, it's the name
of the variable. And again, we follow the rules and we follow the recommendations that
is cable case.
And in this in these series of videos, we'll follow the recommendations as if their rules
are always say that because it just gives you that tighter hold on the syntax, right?
And you're able to understand and read someone else scored that much easily and quickly,
right?
So again, my rule for this series is just follow the rules, follow the recommendations rather
sorry.
If it is it, let's follow the recommendations as if their rules, right?
So so identify, obviously we know the rules and recommendations now, but what a data
types now, that is the type of data you're going to store, right?
And in Java, we have these eight primitive data types and I'm going to just type them
out for you so that you understand what are the data types in Java, right?
So if you have a look at my screen now.
So in terms of their hierarchy, in terms of their size, I'm going to list them out
for you.
So starting with byte, right?
And then we have short, we have a care, we have int, we have float, we have double and
we have long as well.
And because I just wrote them in the hierarchy.
So after in, we also have long, right?
And these folks here, that is byte, short, and as well as int and long, you can use them
to store integer data, right, numbers, that is.
And care is for character data type, that is, it's a two, two byte, Unicode character
in Java, and float and double now are for precision numbers, right, that is with points.
And then long as I said, I'll just remove it from here because I just wrote it, right,
there for you.
So these are if you see one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, I'm missing a data type that
is byte, short, care, int, long, float, and double, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
the one that I'm missing currently is, that is byte, is so, okay, yeah, that is Boolean.
And it takes the values true and false, right.
So these are the eight primitive data types in Java.
So byte is which takes one byte in memory.
This byte also takes one byte, but for numbers, short takes two bytes.
If you have a slightly large number to be stored, care is two bytes, int is four bytes
and long as eight bytes, and then float, we have four bytes, and if you have a slightly larger
precision number, decimal number, then you would have double there to be stored.
So these are the data types, if we call them in Java.
And like the language itself, data types in Java are platform independent, right.
That's unlike other languages where let's say you're working in a C environment, int data
type on a 16 bit machine would take two bytes, but on a 32 it would take more bytes.
But in Java, across architecture, across hardware, the data types are going to be the
same in terms of size, right.
That's why I say they like the language itself, their platform independent.
So that is no matter which platform you're going to use, you're going to find them the
same, right.
So we're going to our environment and now following the syntax, if I come in this out and
that's the comment and comment is obviously the line would not be executed in for a single
line comment.
This is the shortcut that is slash slash and the shortcut is control slash, right.
See, uncomment, if you again press it, control slash is coming to right, see, comment
and uncomment.
So control slash.
And if you want to put in multi line comments, then you're going to just put in something
like this.
So slash star and then at then star slash, right.
These are multi line comments.
Now, following this syntax, what I'll do is is let's say I want to store bullions.
So I'll just say Boolean, not here, but within my code here.
So I'll say Boolean, let's just call it black, that's how you declare a variable in Java.
And the rule is because Java is a strictly typed language that is a variable needs to be
declared before you can use it again to reiterate any variable that you're going to use.
It needs to be declared before we can use it.
And that's why I'm declaring that the syntax is first define the data, right?
And then the name of the variable.
And how do you initialize it?
That is variable name is equal to that is assignment operator and then value.
And I'm just going to say flat assignment operator that's put in the value true, right?
Similarly, you could have combined these two lines that is declaration and introilization
on the same line. So what I could have done is I could have directly said, that's it, right?
And you can declare multiple variables at the same line by separating them with a comma.
I can just say, for example, second, and I've left second, whereas uninitialized, because
I think that it might be like sometime later on and that's what we find.
But the only rule is that the second word should be of the same type as the first variable.
Like there are multiple types like this, then an error, then there needs to be a separator
that is a semi column. And that's perfectly fine, right?
So similarly, I've just said in second word to 900 and by the way, just a note to be taken
here is these are like hard coded values that you put right there in the program and they're
never recommended. Why? Because it just makes your program one dimensional because this flag
would always be false at the start.
The second word would always be 900, right? So rather we should take user input wherever
we can. And how do you take user input from runtime and Java that's coming on for you
in the next video? But for now, just for demonstration, this is how you initialize a variable.
And if you want to print it out, I'll just say the system without a print ln. And rather
than typing the entire thing, you have a shortcut in IntelliJ, that is a south. Say, just
say a south, it means a control set and just say a south enter. That's it. If you were working
in the eclipse, the shortcut says out SYS or UT, but in IntelliJ, it's just south. And
IntelliJ's IntelliSense has always been, has always been so much easier, so much captivating
because you just type in and the suggestions come and see, you just say SYS, system comes
in, right, or system color. And then it keeps on trimming down the results as you type
in. I'll just say system T. See, only the things with system and starting with T comment,
right. So that is the IntelliSense you get with IntelliJ. So system or a print ln again,
I just use south and I'll just want to print the variable value. I'll just say black.
Let's go on and run this. You don't need to save it in IntelliJ. That's the other benefit.
Otherwise, control S is the shortcut. I'll just say controller. See, hello world on the next
line and we do get a false. And similarly, I can say a south, I want to print the value of the
second where I'll just say run, you got on screen. See, just remove extra where I'll say
controller false and the 900, which is the current value of this variable, right. So, and
similarly, you can declare other types. And not just at the top wherever you require them,
I want to declare a variable of type that's a float. I can just go on and say float. Let's
call it, for example, F 278 by 90. And immediately you got an error. Now, take a moment and guess
why we got an error. So we get an error because precision numbers in Java by default are of the
type double, not float, right. And that's why the compiler is your new new friend is unhappy. It
says, it says that on the right, you're putting a double into a left variable that is a float and
that's a mismatch. You hover on this gives you that a required type float provided double,
right. Because precision numbers by default in Java or type double, so there are two ways to go
around this. The first one is just put in a F here and that works. And here a capital F works
as well, because you're signaling to the compiler, this is a float value. Please treat it as a
float. And here a small and a capital works, but otherwise Java is a case sensitive language,
but here both of them work. The other way would have been that is if you still want to treat it as
a double, just change the variable type here to a double. And now you're putting a double value
into a double variable. The compiler is happy. You go on and print it and rather than just printing
the variable value, I want something to make sense on my console. So I want to say value of F is
and just say concatenate. That is F. Double F, let's go on and run this and do we get it? Yes,
see, this is false and I know we don't know what these are, but we now know the 78.9 is the value
of the variable F. And this is how we concatenate it, right. In Java operator overloading is not
permissible. The spread is was stopped with C++, right, but there is a variable which by default
is overloaded. That is the plus operator. It sometimes does the addition and it other times does
the concatenation. And one does it know what to do. It's quite intelligent to know. So that is if
it sees on both sides of the operator, there is the string value, it concatenates. If it sees
there is a string and then there is a variable value, for example, a double in a long, then it
concatenates, right. Otherwise it does addition when there are both numbers of the operands or
both numbers. So that's how you can just use these variables, right. And similarly, short,
byte, long, you can use them as you go along.